[Music]
whether 6% of premature mortality is
related to physical inactivity 9% or
even
15% these estimates are all predicated
on the presumption that the associations
found linking inactivity to death rates
and observational studies constitute
cause and effect I surprised by how much
controversy there is in the medical
literature over whether or not the
apparent longevity benefits of exercise
are even real a classic study from the
1950s entitled coronary heart disease
and physical activity of work
illustrates how difficult it can be to
tease out cality between physical
activity and Longevity London bus
drivers appeared to have twice the risk
of dying from heart disease compared to
bus conductors who were presumed to be
protected by their climbing up down 500
to 700 steps a day in the famous double
deckers however it was later revealed in
a follow-up paper physique of London
busmen that based on the measurements of
their starting uniforms the bus driver
started out significantly heavier
similar issues surrounding reverse
causality continue to haunt
observational exercise studies to this
day is exercising enabling good health
in seniors or is good health Health
enabling exercise in the first place is
inactivity leading to chronic disease or
is chronic disease leading to inactivity
then there are the confounding factors
The Arc typo one being less smoking
among active individuals with the
exception of elite male power athletes
who may die up to nearly five times the
normal rate perhaps due to the use of
vabo steroids athletes tend to live
longer than their sedentary counterparts
as much as 4 to 8 years longer but think
of all the complicating elements
especially among professionals major
league baseball players tour defron
cyclists and Champion skiers all live
longer than the general population but
that doesn't mean it necessarily has
anything to do with home runs Bas or the
slopes maybe it's partly the superior
genetic constitutions that allow for
such physical Feats in the first place
or the socioeconomic status bestowed
upon the winners yes Olympic medalists
live longer than the general population
but so do Grand masters of Chess as
revealed by a study subtitled mind
versus Muscle suggesting it's the
afforded status rather than the muscular
exertion winners of a Nobel Prize or an
Oscar award similarly have Superior life
expectancy to try to tease out these
factors researchers have compared the
effects of Leisure Time physical
activity to occupational physical
activity if the link between exercise
and Longevity were truly causal then the
context within which you get the same
exertion shouldn't matter as you can
probably guess though manual labor can
sometimes be associated with a shorter
not longer life again suggesting the
Primacy of confounders like
socioeconomic factors is it Poss
possible that a genetic predisposition
to physical thickness is what accounts
for the exercise longevity link rather
than the physical activity itself in
other words is it just genetic selection
bias we know exercise and Longevity are
associated with one another but instead
of exercise causing the
longevity maybe the same genetic
predisposition to exercise also leads to
longevity whether or not you actually
exercise at all this question was raised
by a pair of mindblowing studies the
first involved the comparison of two
strains of rats one bred to have high
intrinsic running capacity and the other
bred to have low running capacity then
they were randomized to either get a
running wheel or not even without
exercise the high Fitness ability rats
lived longer than those with low Fitness
ability but unexpectedly the vision of
running wheels so they could all
exercise voluntarily cut the lives of
both strains short running reduced their
life expectancy using twin studies we
can show that there are also genetic
predispositions to exercise in humans
too when identical twins leave home to
start their separate lives their
exercise habits are much more likely to
be concordant than fraternal twins
meaning if one twin vigorously exercises
then the other twin is more likely to do
the same if they share 100% of their DNA
instead of just 50% like regular
brothers and
sisters how could we tell if it's this
genetic predisposition exercise rather
than the actual exercise that accounts
for athletic longevity well what about
the rare cases of identical twins whose
exercise habits
diverge with the same DNA would intense
physical activity make a difference
apparently not the same mortality rates
were found in identical twins whether
they exercise vigorously or not a
critical analysis on whether physical
activity is a cause of longevity
concluded the Undisputed healthrelated
benefits of exercise have yet to
translate into any proven causal
relationship with
longevity this was based on the fact
that though randomized control trials in
clinical populations suffering mostly
from neurological conditions have shown
a drop in premature death rates exercise
interventions have failed to show
exercise extends life among apparently
healthy
individuals however these are difficult
studies to run uh take the largest such
study where more than 1500 older men and
women average age 73 were randomized to
one of three groups for 5 years a
recommendation to just follow the
national guidelines of 30 minutes a day
5 days a week or to replace two of those
weekly sessions with 50 minute sessions
or to replace two of those weekly
sessions with four 4minute bursts of
high-intensity interval training at 90%
of peak heart rate and there ended up
being no difference in mortality rates
between the two extra exercise groups
and the control group this may be
because the control group ended up
exercising so much the control group
advised exercise for just 30 minutes
ended up exercising more than the group
told to boost weekly sessions up to 50
minutes all participants had the
potential to be randomized to the
high-intensity group and so the enroles
had to be pretty fit at Baseline and
with expectations of health checks at
years 1 three and five the control group
stepped it up so much it blurred the
distinctions between the three groups
[Music]